Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the plain bagel. As you might
have heard, there's been a bit of a gold
rush in the markets lately. No, I'm not
talking about AI stocks or Bitcoin, but
this time actual gold. Uh because the
precious metal has seen its price surge
year to date by over 60%, reaching a new
all-time high of nearly $4,400 earlier
this week. Riley, that's even extended
to silver, which itself has surged by a
similar degree to new all-time highs.
And we've seen a real mania around the
shiny metal. People have been circling
blocks lining up outside of gold dealers
in Australia and Vietnam. Interest in
buy gold searches have reached all-time
highs. I decided to crack this out of
the uh costume box. Uh even Donald Trump
has gotten in on the action accumulating
gold himself on the walls of the Oval
Office. I'll be I've been informed that
some of it is just plastic spray painted
that color, which is a bit awkward to be
caught with uh faking gold like that. Uh
by the way, this is a dollar bill. I
don't know if you saw that, but I'm
going to take this off. But amid all
this euphoria about the shiny metal, a
fairly concerning narrative has been
making the rounds and gaining traction
around why people are ultimately buying
this asset. The so-called debasement
trade. The idea that amid ballooning
deficits, political turmoil, and gold
buying activity from central banks, that
the rise in gold's price actually
reflects a world that's preparing for
the inevitable collapse or replacement
of the US dollar. that we are fast
approaching the end of the old world
order and quickly reaching the beginning
of the
older world order I guess because we're
talking about gold here. So which is it?
Are we simply seeing the latest market
fad or are we truly heading towards a
new golden age for better or for worse?
Well, that's what we'll try to decipher
in today's video, to discuss gold as an
investment class, the different
narratives around why it's reaching new
all-time highs, and some considerations
worth going through before you really
subscribe to either story here. A quick
thank you to Brilliant for sponsoring
today's video. Stick around until the
end to learn about how you can start
learning math, coding, and other topics
for free and get a discount on an annual
subscription. Before hopping into it,
let's start with a highle overview of
why investors generally buy gold in the
first place. If this is something that
you're familiar with, you can skip the
section using the timestamps in the
description down below. But for the
uninitiated, the idea of buying gold as
an investment probably seems pretty
bizarre. After all, gold doesn't produce
any sort of cash flow or yield. And
while it does have those industrial uses
that gives it that sort of commodity
value, 44% of demand is simply for
financial purposes with roughly a fifth
of all gold ever mined simply being held
by central banks. So why is it that
people park their money in this very
specific precious metal? Well, there are
a few reasons for it. For one, the
market tends to view gold as a safe
haven investment. That is something that
will retain or even grow its value
during periods of turmoil. Historically,
for example, the precious metal has
passed key price levels during periods
of market stress, passing $1,000 an
ounce with the onset of the great
financial crisis, $2,000 during the CO9
pandemic, and $3,000 earlier this year
with Trump's initial tariff roll out.
It's also, of course, fairly rare with
gold's total supply only growing by
about 2% annually. And part of that is
actually recycled gold. So, it's not
even all just new gold coming out of the
ground. So, because of that, gold is
also viewed as an inflation hedge or
something that again will retain its
value when fiat currencies are losing
theirs. But by far the biggest reason
why gold gets this treatment is simply
its history. the mere inertia of having
previously been treated as a financial
asset or form of money. Something that
goes back thousands of years with it
being widely coveted for jewelry and
religious institutions historically for
its non-corrosive properties and luster
with it up until the 1900s being used
for coinage or to otherwise back the
value of money with it even today still
being held by central banks to help
support the value of their currencies.
Now, of course, with developed countries
having abandoned the gold standard in
the 1970s, there's long been some
controversy over the role of gold in the
modern economy, with some viewing it as
a relic of a time long past, much like
sea shells or rice. While others are
adamant that even today, it's the only
form of money worth anything. But this
debate over gold is really nothing new.
So-called gold bugs or gold enthusiasts
have been rooting for its resurgence for
quite some time. But what's fueling the
precious metal rally today? What's
brought it back in fashion? Well,
probably not this. Uh, but Donald Trump
has interestingly played a role in the
price resurgence. As mentioned,
investors tend to flock to the precious
metal during periods of uncertainty. And
well, look around. For one, there's the
economic uncertainty. As we all know,
Trump's tariffs have been causing quite
a bit of upheaval for global supply
chains uh for most of this year. And
recently, we've seen tensions reignite
between China and the United States,
with Trump threatening a 100% tariff
against Chinese goods starting November
1st. And while the boomound AI has
certainly bolstered activity in the
economy, a number of analysts have been
ringing the alarm bells warning of a
potential recession just around the
corner. with Goldman Sachs putting the
probability of a recession over the next
12 months at 20% as of September. JP
Morgan putting the odds at 40% as of
July and one UBS analyst putting the
probability at a staggering 93% as of
September with some even buying gold as
a hedge against this supposed AI bubble.
The idea that with valuations being so
high for AI stocks and so much
unsustainable activity in the space that
there's the risk of a severe correction
with some investors choosing to hide
their money in anticipation. But one of
the main economic concerns being flagged
as driving some gold demand here is
government debt loads which have reached
very high levels with deficits
continuing to expand and with interest
rates still being fairly high. The
interest burden of that debt alone risks
causing some problems. Something that
would only be exacerbated by a
recession. So that's the first thing.
There's a lot of anxieties around the
state of the economy. A second factor
driving this gold demand has been the
political uncertainty, headlined again
by none other than Donald Trump, whose
unconventional whiplash policies and
actions have raised concerns over
America's checks and balances and the
overall integrity of the US dollar. With
there being particular concern over
Trump's targeting of the Federal
Reserve, with Donald Trump having
publicly criticized and attempted to
pressure Jerome Powell to cut interest
rates and having attempted to fire
Federal Reserve board member Lisa Cook
over seemingly unfounded mortgage fraud
allegations, with the intent there
seeming to be to replace her with
someone more willing to follow Donald
Trump's direction. In addition to the
concerns around the Federal Reserve,
there's also the government shutdown,
which has recently become the second
longest in history with Democrats and
Republicans refusing to compromise on a
spending bill to keep the government
open. Something that seemingly helped
get gold across the $4,000 mark earlier
this month. And importantly, it's not
just the US experiencing political
turmoil here. Uh in France, the Euro
zone's second largest economy, we've
seen the country go through four
different prime ministers in less than
two years amid political divides in
parliament. With even the current prime
minister having recently resigned only
to be later reappointed and with the
appointment of a stimulusfriendly prime
minister in Japan, there are concerns
that the debt heavy country will see
further deficits in the future with both
these countries seeing their bond yields
increase representing weak demand for
government bonds. So with all this
uncertainty, you can see why many
investors have been migrating to gold
here as a safe haven asset. But there's
one other important buyer in the market
that's in part been fueling this rally,
and that is central banks. You see,
following the abandonment of the gold
standard, we saw a general trend of
central banks offloading their gold
reserves. With the US dollar ultimately
replacing gold as a key reserve asset.
Over the last few years, central banks
have become the biggest buyers of the
precious metal, buying at their fastest
pace since at least the 1950s. With the
past 3 years, each seeing over 1,000
tons of bullion being purchased by the
institutions, with the total gold held
by central banks estimated to sit around
36,000 metric tonses. In fact, you might
have seen the headline that for the
first time since 1996, central banks now
hold more gold in their reserves than US
treasuries. And some have speculated
that's the central bank mine activity
that's ultimately spurring investors to
jump into the space with many retail
investors getting exposure via gold ETFs
rather than actually owning the precious
metal. These investment vehicles offer
share representations of physical gold
and have had a record year of buying
activity in just the first 9 months of
2025 with more than $60 billion flowing
into gold ETFs so far. Albeit total
assets in gold ETFs do remain below
their 2020 peak when the pandemic was
fueling a lot more holding. So we really
are seeing buying from all fronts here
from institutions, retail and central
banks. But it brings us back to the
debate about what this all ultimately
represents with some again highlighting
that this reflects the ultimate
debasement trade. Currency debasement
refers to the historical practice of
rulers slowly eroding trust in their
currency by mixing gold and silver coins
with less valuable metals. Something
that's argued to have contributed to the
collapse of the Roman Empire in 476 AD.
even though that did technically happen
200 years after the coin stopped having
meaningful gold or silver content. And
as the name implies, some have argued
that with the current ballooning US debt
load, uh the weaponization of the dollar
against Russia in 2022, and political
instability in general, the US dollar is
slowly being debased with many
referencing the 10% decline in the value
of the US dollar this year alone, the
fact that the dollar's makeup of foreign
reserves has been decreasing, and of
course, the surge in gold's value. We've
had a lot of big names adding fire to
this narrative, even if not directly
supporting it. Ken Griffin of Citadel,
Ray Dallio of Bridgewater, and Jaime
Diamond of JP Morgan have all
highlighted the risks of the US debt
situation, noting gold's role to varying
degrees in hedging against these risks.
So with these narratives, all this
interest, and of course the price chart,
it's very easy to get caught up in this
narrative. And there is of course a
chance that gold continues to rise in
price from here. But before you
subscribe to the most extreme narratives
here around dollar debasement and the
like, there are a few things worth
considering. For one, while individual
investors may of course be buying gold
for any assortment of reason, there's
not a whole lot of evidence that the
debasement trade is what's driving most
market activity here. In terms of the
dollar being down this year, we haven't
actually seen much movement in the
dollar index since April, while gold has
seen roughly half of its massive surge
during that period. And the dollar
itself is still roughly flat from 3
years ago. So that decline doesn't
really explain gold's massive price
appreciation. In fact, if you price gold
in terms of oil barrels, you can see
that even when you strip out the dollar,
the metal's value has surged
dramatically. We also haven't really
seen any changes in inflation
expectations, suggesting that uh gold's
surge in price doesn't really reflect a
basease scenario of runaway prices. In
terms of US Treasury bonds, their yields
don't really reflect this abandonment to
the dollar. In fact, treasury bonds have
actually increased in price since May.
Also brings us to another important
point around the foreign reserves of
central banks. Well, yes, it is true
that gold has replaced US Treasury bonds
in terms of value that has more so to do
with the surge in gold's price rather
than the quantity of gold held
increasing meaningfully. Remember,
gold's price has more than doubled over
the past couple of years. So, it's not
really surprising that its share of
these reserve market values has
increased relative to treasury bonds
which have been relatively flat. And
that's just treasury bonds, a type of US
asset. But US dollars continue to be the
number one foreign reserve asset with
there being roughly 7 trillion in US
dollars held versus the roughly $5
trillion in gold. Now, we are seeing the
dollar's share of total foreign reserves
decrease over time, and that's certainly
been exacerbated by recent events, but
it's far from having been replaced at
this point. And there's also a really
important point around which central
banks are actually buying gold here.
Because while headlines might give this
impression that nations around the world
are rushing to buy gold here, that's
really not the case. The biggest buyers
of gold year to date have been Poland,
Kazakhstan, and Turkey, with China,
India, and Russia also being notable
buyers over the past few years. But
these countries don't really reflect
global interest in gold. According to a
World Gold Council survey, while the
percentage of countries looking to
increase their gold reserves has been on
the rise, most central banks aren't
planning to increase their gold
allocation. And those that are tend to
be from emerging markets and developing
economies. So you are seeing a handful
of countries aggressively accumulating
gold, some of which do have a very
active interest in moving away from the
US dollar. And the percentage of
countries interested has again been
increasing. We haven't seen as much
buyin from the larger world powers. And
that kind of makes sense. The reason
central banks have foreign currencies on
hand is to allow them the liquidity to
transact quickly when enacting policy.
And while gold is a fairly liquid asset,
it can still drag down the price to have
to sell before doing these transactions
compared to just having US dollars or
even treasuries which can be borrowed
against very easily. And while it's
great to hold an asset that's
appreciating in value, it might not be a
smart allocation to jump in after we've
seen this volatile price appreciation.
Not to mention, it's a costly asset to
store and doesn't generate any sort of
income while you're holding it. And
what's interestingly looked over quite a
bit is while there's often this debate
of the US dollar versus gold or other
alternative assets, the US central bank
is actually the one set to gain the most
from gold's price appreciation given
that they currently own the largest
amount globally. So, some initial
thoughts around the debasement trade and
why you should be skeptical of this sort
of overarching narrative. Uh the second
big consideration here is that while
gold is often treated by investors as
this safe and secure store of value,
it's worth highlighting that
historically that property hasn't always
held. It's easy to get caught up in the
belief that because of gold's rarity,
its value will mathematically increase
over time as the dollar experiences
inflation. But in the past, there have
been extended periods where gold's value
has fallen against the US dollar with
there being a 20-year period starting in
the 1980s where gold fell in price. And
something being scarce doesn't
inherently draw demand. Uh platium, for
example, is a metal that's actually 30
times more rare than gold that currently
trades at a third of gold's price.
Because again, a lot of gold's demand is
based on its historical inertia, not
strictly speaking, its scarcity. And
with the sharp increase in gold's price
that we've seen, there's naturally the
risk of a correction. Bank of America
analysts have highlighted that this sort
of price movement has only occurred
three times before historically, each of
which were followed by 20 to 33%
declines. And at least one of those
declines was actually fueled by central
banks themselves. A sell-off that only
ended when they signed the Washington
agreement, agreeing to limit how much
gold they would sell. And while it's
certainly too early to call it a
reversal, we have already seen the
middle drop over 5% from its peak
reached earlier this week, demonstrating
that this safe haven asset can get quite
volatile when people are rushing into
it. But it brings us to the ultimate
question, Richard, where does gold's
price go from here? Uh to which I would
respond, I have no idea. Again, as
mentioned, hopefully it goes to
emphasize that the price of the asset is
really based on future demand trends,
which are hard to determine. If we see a
cooling of the political and economic
environment, or interestingly, if we see
rising yields, which itself could
demonstrate a weakness for US
treasuries, those are all factors that
have been highlighted as things that
could lead to a cooling of gold prices.
And with gold price surging amid a
seeming perfect storm of factors, the
reversal of any one of these things,
whether it be a trade deal with China or
a reopening of the government, could
contribute to a pullback. But the truth
is that we just don't know where things
will go from here. Whether the political
situation will continue to heat up or if
we see agreements around tariffs and
trade deals. Because there's so many
factors at play, it's impossible to
predict the demand trends for something
like gold over time. And historically,
you can see that demand has fluctuated
quite a bit. Now, it's not to say
everyone buying gold right now has this
sort of doom and gloom expectation. Some
are just buying it as this hedge against
tail risks, something that they're
willing to spend the money and
potentially lose it for the sake of just
offsetting any sort of, you know,
catastrophic event in the US. But my
point is not to argue that gold's price
won't increase or that it's certainly
going to decrease from here, but rather
just to highlight the risks given that
many people view this as the ultimate
store of value, something that over time
has maintained its worth when that
hasn't been a guarantee. Thank you for
watching. And before I sign off, you
like charts. You get your dopamine hits
from a good XY axis. What about AI?
Curious how AI does that thing? Well,
what if I told you that you could learn
more about the inner workings of these
things and how many other subjects
worked? That's right, because today's
sponsor, Brilliant, offers a learning
platform for subjects ranging from math
and data science to AI and programming.
Now, of course, learning platforms are
nothing new, but what's really unique
about Brilliant is that they focus on
active participation. that is
incorporating activities that allow you
to play with the concept and work
through exercises to enhance your
understanding of the topic rather than
just having you watch two-hour lecture
videos. Their data module, for example,
covers everything from data
visualizations to statistical models and
measurements. But the activities
visualizing what can otherwise be fairly
difficult to grasp topics. Like I
mentioned, for example, how platforms
like ChatBT use tokens to ultimately run
their AI models. What's also handy is
that the lessons are bite-sized, meaning
you can tackle it in just a few minutes
of dedication a day. Or if you want to
dedicate and push through a topic, you
can put in as much time as you please.
And the best part is that you can try
Brilliant completely free. Just go to
brilliant.org/theplain
bagel, scan the QR code on screen, or
click the link in the description.
Brilliant's also going to give viewers
20% off an annual premium subscription,
which gives you unlimited daily access
to everything on the platform. Thank
you, Brilliant. And thank you guys for
joining me today. I hope you found this
video helpful. If you did, please do
make sure to like, subscribe, all that
good stuff. It does help the channel
tremendously. And let me know your
thoughts on gold. Whether you think it's
a relic of the past or you think it
might beat out the dollar as the top
reserve assets. Personally, I'm hedging
my bets with the uh the golden dollar
dollar bill chain. This was like five
bucks from Amazon, but I'm getting my
money's worth. Thanks again for joining
me and as always, be safe out